hello and welcome it's April 3rd 2024
we're here in active inference guest
stream
78.1
discussing what could come before time
with Juan Diego Bogata and this should
be a great presentation followed by a
discussion so thank you again for
joining looking forward to the
presentation and
discussion thank you Daniel so uh hello
everybody so my name is ju and today I'm
going to talk about mainly phenomenology
no so much about not so much about
active inference but maybe all
discussion will go that way I kind of
assume so to give you a bit of context
about this so uh this presentation is
actually based on a paper that I
recently published in phenomenology and
the Cog Sciences uh last month but to
give you a bit more context uh in
general I'm interested in the
relationship between cognitive science
and
phenomenology and when I talk about
phenomenology I'm very mindful about the
fact that this is a term that is a bit
ambiguous in the literature because if
you talk to maybe philosophers of mind
or cognitive scientists when they talk
about phenomenology they often think
about say qualia or you know the what
it's like of uh phenomenal Consciousness
and that's okay but I usually use that
term to refer to specific philosophical
tradition and known as phenomenology
that was started uh towards the
beginning of the 20th century by Edmund
husel and it was further developed by
people like meron or haiger or Simon De
and the whole point of phenomenology is
to try to provide a very strict and
rigorous analysis of Consciousness and
live the experience uh by taking very
very seriously the first person
perspective so it's a matter of trying
to unveil the invariant structures of
Consciousness and I think that this
methodology is quite promising for us to
uh better understand uh cons
Consciousness and cognition so it might
be an interesting thing to further
integrate into our scientific
understanding of the mind and I think
that a good way of connecting
phenomenology with the broader kind of
iral context of the of the cognitive
Sciences uh is the inactive approach
mainly because uh people like Francisco
Aela or Evan Thompson were very have
been very influenced by phenomenologists
like whoer andan when it comes to ideas
like embodiment uh the embeddedness of
cognition um the importance of
subjectivity these kind of stuff and in
this particular talk I want to focus on
uh something that these two Frameworks
have in common which is uh how they
characterize intentionality so usually
uh in cognitive science philosophy of
mind when we talk about intentionality
we mean kind of this directedness or
aboutness of certain mental States so
there's this kind of uh relationship
between the mind and specific object in
the world and that's that's uh kind of
um uh the usual concept of
intentionality but I think that
phenomenologists and quite a bit of
activists have a bit of a broader
conceptualization of intentionality not
only as this aboutness that is directed
towards a specific object in the world
but rather as a general openness to the
world and the whole idea of
phenomenology is precisely to identify
the structures that uh constitute that
openness and that's again that's kind of
the context of my presentation and my
paper uh but when you look at the kind
of the literature in classical
phenomenology and you notice that
there's one particular structure or
feature of lived experience that has
some sort of Primacy and that's
temporality or as whoer calls it time
Consciousness so here I bring a quote of
P what do you mean there's like multiple
kind of
overlaid oh hold on visual frames I'll
try again thank
you I was entertaining the possibility
it was intentional oh no yeah I don't
know what
happened let me try
again yeah looks good thank you okay
fantastic okay so now without the
overlay so here have H quote of feral
talking about time Consciousness uh he
says that in the ABCs of the
Constitution of all objectivity given to
Consciousness and subjectivity as
existing for itself time Consciousness
is the a if consist as we might say in a
universal formal framework in a
synthetically constituted form in which
all other possible syntheses most
participate and this a very kind of
fancy and worthy way of saying that you
know if you want to understand
Consciousness uh from its first person
perspective the first thing you have to
analyze is temporality that's kind of
the basis of it all and the reason why
uh we should start by temporality is
because not only we tend to experience
things as unfolding in time but also
because
uh Consciousness itself is a stream of
Consciousness it's a temporal unfolding
and that kind of uh frames all of our
experiences so temporality is kind of
the the fundamental structure of of
Consciousness uh and when we get deeper
into the hustan analysis of temporality
we tend to find this uh triarte
structure of time Consciousness so who
tend to say that what he calls the Liv
the living present which is literally
how experience the present right now is
usually an integration of the past the
present and the future the just past the
immediate present and what is about to
come and these have like very specific
terminologies we call a retention the
kind of this experience of the just past
paral impression experience of what is
literally happening right now in like a
very uh small uh now phase of perception
and protention to the anticipation of
what it's about to come and well these
different kind of operation of
Consciousness have very complex uh
relationships I'm not going to dwell too
much into them the whole point is that
they together constitute the kind of the
flowing feature of Consciousness how it
flows temporally how it's kind of um
sinking into the past because we on
we're constantly anticipating what is
about to come this anticipation is
usually implicit we don't necessarily uh
think about what is about to come
explicitly it just kind of happens but
when you experience something this uh
like the the Primal impression either
confirms or fulfills what we were
pretending or anticipating or negates
the anticipation and regardless of that
whether there is anticipation or
fulfillment uh what is experienced kind
of sinks into the past and this is
called retentional modification so we
have this kind of continuous flow of
time that goes from the future towards
the past sinking into the past but
importantly this um this constitution of
of the living present or the flow of
time can be be conceptually understood
as pretemporal or atemporal because the
whole point is that this these processes
these operations are literally
constituting our experience of time so
they cannot be given in time such
because if you if you claim that then
you have um uh a circular
argument uh who nevertheless recognizes
that this structure the structure of
time Consciousness is just an
abstraction it's just a formal framework
that has to be further um complemented
by qualitative content so even though
time time Consciousness kind of the
basis of it all we have to go beyond in
order to better understand Consciousness
and when we talk about content we have
to talk about affection so for feral
affection is the lure given to
Consciousness The Peculiar pool that an
object given to Consciousness exercises
on the ego it is a pool that is relaxed
when the ego turns towards it
attentively so it's just like in in very
simple terms affection occurs when
something in our field of of perception
our perceptual field kind of tries to
catch our attention we feel this kind of
solicitation or pull or tendency or
disposition to pay attention to
something um and for Co this this this
process of affection corresponds to the
basic form of intentionality because
that's literally when we first have this
directness towards an object it's a
first moment which is an object becomes
Salient for us and it also gives rise to
the minimum form of activity which is
attention so there's this distinction
between affection and attention for me
to attend something to being able to uh
being attentive towards an object that
object should try to call my attention
has to affect me beforehand logically
not temporal it's like a logical
relationship in here so that's why we
can H conceive of affection as this kind
of precondition of attention and to
better give you uh an illustration of
what affection is you can see this it's
the the flag of Japan and probably when
you see the flag of Japan the thing that
catches your attention the most is the
red circle in the middle and the reason
why this catches our attention is
because of the very very Stark um
contrast between the circle and the
background the white background so in a
lot of cases very like in sensorial
cases affection is related to this
contrast compare this to saying um an
artwork by Jackson Pollock in this case
there's there's a bunch of pain strokes
and there's nothing that is specifically
catching your attention maybe you're
seeing the yellow then the red and the
black it's like chaos and and the reason
why this happens at least from
phenomenological perspective is because
uh there's no there's no there is
contrast but it's not as strong as in
this case of course again this is like a
very basic case we can also introduce uh
interest and concerns sometimes
something catches our attention just
because uh it's relevant for our current
interests so for instance now I'm very
focused on the screen of my laptop and
it's precis because I'm interested in
giving this presentation so this is
broadly what affection means this kind
of felt felt P or tendency towards an
object or like a sensory content in our
con in our uh perceptual
field now the importance of affection
lies in the fact that the world is first
properly given and experienc through it
for something to be experienced it must
affect me so this kind of shows the
importance of of affection in relation
to temporality temporality provides the
form framework that organizes uh
experiential content but for us to
experience something at all there has to
be affection and I like to to link the
the hustan concept of affection to the
broader con concept of affectivity and I
borrow jaavan colet's concept of
affectivity it's not only about emotions
or mood or this different kind of
effective States but rather it's a
broader Dimension that she defines as a
lack of indifference and in this case we
can say that affection in theeran sess
is completely consistent with
affectivity because when something
affects us then we are no longer
indifferent to it so that's effectivity
in the broadest and most basic of Senses
but importantly uh for H and I would say
that for other classical
phenomenologists affection still
presupposes time conscience temporality
mainly because uh for something to
affect us uh it has to occur has to be
given in the impressional present so
then our phas it also affirms this
orientation toward the future this
tendency towards attention it's
solicitation towards the future so it
presupposes protention and there's also
a relationship with retention but I'm
not going to dwell too much into that
the whole point about this is that uh
given that affection still presupposes
time Consciousness we can say this H
would say temporality is the most basic
uh structure of uh Consciousness so if
we can want to do cognitive science or
Consciousness research we should
probably start by temporality and
interestingly if we go to uh the an
active approach and velas neurop
phenomenology which is a way of trying
to integrate phenomenological research
with uh neurobiological research by
establishing reciprocal constraints
between these two domains
uh the first neurophenomenological study
and Analysis that barela developed is
precisely of time Consciousness and he
considers it to be kind of an acid test
for the neurophenomenological project
but there's some differences between how
barela and Hil conceive of
temporality whereas for Hil temporality
is kind of abstract formal framework
that is always organizing our
experiences Vela very clearly states
that
embodied activity gives temporality its
roots in living itself so that's kind of
an active gimmick isn't it uh we have
for Vela what actually gives rise to
experience of time is the fact that
we're embodied beings that are um
relating their where interacted with the
world through action and an example of
this is something like the do grait
illusion so sometimes you see a dog
sometimes you see a rabbit and but I
would say that this shift which is a
temporal shift we can actually
experience kind of the temporal
unfolding of how our percept uh changes
over time for rather lot this shift uh
occurs because there's action going on
usually um very minimal and often
unnoticed action for for example visual
Sackets or you know maybe just Shi your
attention a bit and that changes the
whole percept and this kind of shows for
bellaa that we actually have to to focus
on this embodied activity that gives
rise to this constant temporal enfold
of how we perceive the
world and the kind of the whole point of
neurophenomenology is to try to look at
what's happening at the neural level and
what Vela says or he he discovers is
that if you look at the neural dynamics
that uh underpin this embodied activity
and you describe them through the tools
of dynamical System Theory the kind of
model you get you know uh trajectory in
state space these Dynamics would mirror
will will probably mirror the structure
of the living present as it is analyzed
by fer so we have this kind of almost
isomorphic relationship between the
Dynamics of uh the neurodynamics that
underpin embod activity and the Dynamics
of time Consciousness which for barela
suggests that that's precisely where we
can find the reciprocal constraining
between phenomenology and
neurobiology uh but there is an
important distinction between another
important distinction between Vela and
hell here whereas for hell at least in
the classical texts in which he analyzes
time Consciousness protention is kind of
the mirror opposite of of retention so
pretention is kind of this retention
that it's looking to the Future buta
notices that there's something different
about protention for him protention uh
seems to be marked by an affective
tonality and in in the in the 1999 paper
the example he gives is that what he's
trying to write this work with what is
trying to find the correct words he
feels this this tendency this
disposition to look for a very specific
word but it's also marked by frustration
because he cannot really find the proper
uh expression so there's this kind of
correlation between anticipation and the
tendenc towards the future and a feeling
tonality and that's all he says in the N
199 1999 paper he says that I'm just
doing a sketch of this hopefully I'll
work on this in the future and I think
there's two ways in which we can find
kind of the elaborations on these ideas
on the one hand we can borrow from uh
later and active analysis of
emotion uh when you read for example the
work of Evan Thompson or javanna Coletti
they often emphasize the fact that
emotion uh is a process that integrates
a lot of neural and processes including
attention evaluation bodily arousal and
importantly for for what I'm interested
in Act Tendencies and a way to to uh
illustrate this is by borrowing Walter
Pan's Dynamic architecture of the lyic
system so for Freeman if you look at the
Dynamics of brain body and environment
you can find a lot of causal Loops that
constitute H certain cognitive processes
so for instance if we want to understand
action we have to understand how sensory
systems the hippocampus the motor system
systems and the environment from this
caal loop it's a an action perception
Loop mainly and this suggest like that
environment body and brain co-constitute
uh action cognitive action but the
important thing here for me is that all
these Loops all these different uh
proceptive M Loops all go through the
hippocampus which is as you probably
know kind of the one of the most
important parts in the brain that is
related to emotion and this a way of
noticing that all these uh cognitive
processes uh action perception prop
perception are probably at the sub
personal neural level uh colored or
constitut by
emotion and what H Thompson takes from
this is that if you look at the
relationship between the motor system
and the sensory system there has to be
uh what we may call a state of
expectancy because our sensory systems
have to be prepared uh in relation to
the consequences of our actions and this
is kind of very very similar to some of
the claims in the active inference
literature although this is earlier but
that's important because then you have
have this kind of anticipation what it's
about to come at the sensory level at
least at at a neural level and Thompson
says that we can actually link this
neural process to what at the
experiential level phenomenologist
called protention so we start seeing
this connection between protention so
temporality and emotion so affectivity
so we see at a at a
neurophenomenological level how we're
moving beyond just this very formal and
Abstract description of
temporality but even if we look at this
paper by Banda in 2005 they go further
and they analyze the experiential level
of affection and they kind of analyze it
in in in a form as a form of a what they
call a microt temporality so they say
that if you analyze not only kind of the
neural level but also the
phenomenological SL experiential level
you'll find that there's this kind of
very quick uh integration of events you
have the the precipitation of an event
or trigger so something affects you uh
the emergence of salience so
experientially what affects you become
Salient and there's a balanced feeling
tone that's the call effective tality
I've been talking about for a while
already there's motor changes so there's
action tendencies that are formed
towards the object and there's autonomic
physiological changes that kind of bring
everything together and this kind of
this microt temporality actually
constitutes what US calls
affection but from this analysis which
is completely consistent with the neurop
phenomenol analysis I just mentioned uh
V Anda claimed that uh this micro
temporality implies that affection
precedes temporality because it gives
rise to a tendency that can only deploy
itself in time and thus as time and
that's a very cure sentence for me to be
honest I had to read it like a thousand
times when I was reading that paper um
but from what what I can understand and
I think that um at least Evan Thompson
seems to read it very similarly uh is
that what happens with this micr Pro is
that it terms a tendency an action
tendency that precisely is protention so
what we see is that the the this
integration of very quick events at the
that is correlated to the
neurophysiological level are actually
what give rise to to protention and
because protention is kind of the
spearhead of temporality we can say that
affection precedes temporality is kind
of the temporal and logical uh and
empirical um antecedent to temporality
so we have a very different claim uh in
comparison to what Hil and other other
phenomenologists say whereas Hol would
say you know the first the most
important and most basic uh structure of
Consciousness is temporality it seems
like some activist would say no no no no
temporality is super important but it
actually presupposes
affectivity and I think there's
something odd about that claim because
how can affection preced temporality if
it is deployed in time there seems some
sort of paradox going on here how can
that's precisely their claim if you see
here they say affection temporal because
it gives R to to a tendency that can
only deploy itself in time and thus as
time that's they're claiming temporality
emerges in this micro temporality of
affection and I think that there's the
risk of um conflicting two different
temporalities in here there is on the
one hand what we may call objective time
so it's the time of neural processes the
time that neuroscientists use to measure
all these um neural events and Dynamics
and it subjective time so time
Consciousness how we experience the
world and it's problematic to conflate
these two kind of temporalities because
the whole point of phenomenology from
the cons perspective is to find the
structures that actually allow us to
experience time as an objective um
feature of the world and when I say that
there's the risk of completing t two
levels in the inactive uh approach it's
very clear when you see this precisely
the microt temporality if you take a
look at this microt temporality some
events are clearly experiential for
instance the emergence of sence and the
veence feeling tone so we experience the
saleny of objects we experience the
feeling tonality of of what it's like to
be you know a human being that engages
with objects but for instance motor
changes an autonomic physiological
changes seem to be more of a subpersonal
or even neural um process so that's at
the at not at the subjective level but
rather at the objective level so there's
this kind of shift in between the
objective and subjective levels which I
think is what actually gives um kind of
justifies the claim that affection
precedes temporality I mean affection PR
temporality if we understand affection
just as at this level at the level of
neural process and neural Loops but if
we look at it from an experiential
perspective that is not so clear because
we cannot really experience these Loops
we experience kind of the effect you
want to put it like that or kind of what
emerges from these correlations we don't
experience them as such so again saying
that affection put temporality it is as
if we are saying affection a subjective
process objectively precedes another
subjective Pro process and that's where
the compleation kind of uh comes in and
what is interesting about this this
compleation is that if you look at the N
1999 paper of Vela the the one on time
Consciousness he realized there's
something odd about the the relationship
between temporality and affectivity or
emotion as he calls it there calls it
there and he says that maybe what we
have to look for is a what he calls a
nonel uh solution or a non-dual
perspective so we're trying to show that
these two things are not two things
there maybe one or there's some sort of
dialectic going on if you want to put it
like that and it's quite interesting
because again at that point he's saying
I'm just sketching some ideas and then
later on when he publishes the Vela and
the paper of 2005 which is actually like
2002 um there's no non-dual perspective
at all what you find is precisely a dual
perspective According to which
effectivity preceeds
temporality so what I want to do here
now is to try to pursue this n
perspective and show that temporality
and effectivity go hand inand they're
co-emergent but to actually show that we
have to avoid conflating the objective
and the subjective levels and that's the
reason why I focus on the phenomen
olical
level so this brings me back to uh H so
when we're talking about affection it's
very important to notice that uh this
kind of transition from affection to
attention gives rise to uh foreground
background structure in perception and
it's very well noted by gestal
psychologists later on so for instance
in this usual example of G gestal
perception if you focus on the black
shape you will probably see something
like a vas but the this perceptual
meaning the fact that you're perceiving
a black vas vas um it's only possible
because there is also a wi um background
so you have this kind of perceptual
interplay between the foreground and the
background whereas the black uh
foreground the object of attention is
given in a specific way the background
is still given you're experiencing the
the white part but it's not the focus of
your attention and that's very important
because that kind of shows that when we
shift from affection to attention
there's still an affective background
kind of not only pulling trying to pull
our attention but it's also kind of
giving meaning to what we're pering so
that kind of shows that the the object
of attention always presupposes an
effective
background and this not only happens in
like very simple cases like this but
also if we look at a more complex uh
painting
uh there's a lot of different objects
and colors and beautiful kind of uh
sketches and uh that are trying to
precisely pull our attention it's
affection and if you focus for instance
in the face of this girl there's a lot
of colors that are still there and they
they will probably produce a feeling of
I don't know maybe you like the painting
may you think it's beautiful or maybe
you don't like that but this all comes
in the interplay between foreground and
background or between attention and
affection and if we go kind of zoom out
from here and go back to the concept of
intentionality then a phenomenologist
like me would say that this kind of
shows that we can distinguish two
concepts of intentionality that are
always at play there is what we may call
object intentionality which is the usual
way which Phenom in which philosophers
of mind and cognitive scientists talk
about intentionalities this kind of
directedness or aboutness of the Mind
there to specific object in this case it
could be say the face of the girl that's
the intentional object phenomenologists
would say that that's an active
attentive an explicit for intentionality
it is attentive because it's it
presupposes attention it's explicit
because I'm explicitly related to that
I'm thematizing an object and it's
active because in a sense I am the one
who decides what you attend at least at
a very minimal level there's a form of
action but behind this there's always
this effective background or effective
Horizon which is also intentional
because we are experiencing it it's
given or pregiven who would say but it's
easier to think about as given in
experience but it's passive because we
do not decide what affects us it just
kind of happens it's something in our
perceptual field it's effective because
it it um occurs through affection and
it's often implicit because we are not
paying attention to the background
precisely because we are attending the
foreground the background is often
implicit but this this um background is
super super important because it shapes
how we experience the intentional object
if you want to go further um deeper into
into the concept of practive
intentionality you can think about the
experience of your body so prop
perceptive experience we often do not
pay attention to how our body feels but
it's always there in the background it's
affecting us it's like a form of self
affection some phenomenologist would say
and this all comes together precisely to
uh give rise to the specific
experiential meaning of the intentional
object at the level of object
intentionality so this kind of shows
that affection is way more important
than perhaps more complex than initially
thought and to even kind of com uh make
things a bit more complex we can also
take into account the fact that
affection is deeply embodied
so to give you an an
example elaborated by H he says that
every perception that presents the
object to me in this attentional
orientation lives open the Practical
transition to other appearances of the
same object so this practical transition
to other appearance is precisely the the
transition from affection to attention I
can always um thematize or attend what
is affecting me but it as as who would
note this involves practical uh
engagements so he says that the
possibilities of transition are
practical possibilities there is does of
freedom to run through run through the
appearances in such a way that I move my
eyes my head alter the posture of my
body go around the object direct my
regard to it and so on so this shows
that attent affection is not only a like
it's not an abstract pool not an
abstract solicitation It's actually an
embodied solicitation it's not only
trying to uh object trying to catch our
attention and and that's it they're
trying to move us in a very literal
sense and this is kind of very very
familiar to an activist this is
precisely what Vela was trying to point
out when he was saying that uh embodied
activity is at the root of temporality
this is the embod activity he was
thinking about it's already found in the
works of hro and if we take very very
seriously this practical or embodied
nature of of um affection I think that
we end up thinking about the world as
something very similar to um climbing
wall so if you ever been to a Climbing
Center you might encounter something
like this walls full of uh holes and
they have different shapes they have
different colors some of them are very
very difficult to get a hold of some of
them are quite easy there's there's a
lot of stuff going on and all of them
are trying are are quite literally what
eological psychologist would call
affordances they afford different uh
action possibilities and how they afford
how strongly they afford to do that how
strongly they solicit your action
depends on thing depends on things like
uh your skills how skillful you are uh
the kind of body you have or even the
interest you have so if you're trying to
run through a um a specific curse in the
in the um hang in the climbing wall some
holes will be completely irrelevant uh
in relation to the curse you're trying
to to do so they are not as uh affording
as they are as they might be and that's
kind of how I understand the world from
a phenomenological perspective this is
what operative intentionality opens up
the world becomes what ecological
psychologist would call a field of
relevant affordances so again it's just
some affordances are more relevant
because they're important for our
concerns our needs our skills or the
kind of BU body we have that's mainly
the
point and what I like about affordances
is that you can very easily move from
this more eological perspective to a
phenomenological perspective by asking
how AFF forant perception works again
that's a classical phenomenological
question how does this specific form of
experience Works what are its structured
and and as I've done elsewhere I've
analyzed this afford perception as and
interplay between a pull or solicitation
coming from the object so the object is
pulling or solic soliciting a specific
action and a subjective projection of
practical possibilities and this
subjective projection is precisely
uh future oriented projection us would
say that affection has a unitary
tendency toward the future
intentionality is predominantly oriented
toward the future so we might say that
objects appear as affording actions as
soliciting action that's that's
affection but these actions can only be
done in the near future it's an I can in
the future so the projection is not only
bodily but also temporal is a form of
bodily anticipation and this kind of
starts intertwining affection and
temporality in a very very nice way I
think from this perspective I believe
operative intentionality involves the
interplay between effective
solicitations and future oriented or
potential projection of practical
possibility ities The Horizon that
serves as the background of attention
must be experientially understood as a
set of bodily anti
Tendencies so this shows in which sense
for me affectivity and temporality are
co-emergent on the one hand affection
presupposes the potential projection of
bodily possibilities so projection h
potention of temporality shapes
affection but on the other hand
temporality or more specifically prot
tension and anticipation presupposes the
effective disclosure of the world if
nothing were to affect me there would be
no impressional present from which
anticipations are formed so objects are
pulling me right now and it's because
right now there's this effective
tendency that I actually have these
projections and this kind of shows that
affection and protention the spearhead
of temporality presuppose one another
which shows that they're co-emergent
which is precisely what both uh an
activist and phenomenologist can of Miss
I think and this uh I believe that um
has very interesting consequences and to
give you um illustration of what I mean
let's talk about very very briefly about
depression so here I'm borrowing a
figure from a paper by sanan and
colleagues in which they are trying to
sketch different fields of relevant
affordances uh you can ignore the OCD
one I just want to focus on the quote
unquote normal one and the impression
one to each of these bars represents how
soliciting an affordance is affordance
is in the environment so for us if we're
not suffering from um severe depression
some objects or some events in the world
will solicit us more than others there's
a stronger effective tendency there's
stronger need or pull coming from the
object why again depends on our concerns
our interests our bodily skills Etc what
happens in depression is kind of there's
a flattening of the field of relevant
affordances people with depression
struggle a lot with trying to wake up in
the morning or doing everyday tasks
because their world is not from their
perspective is not kind of soliciting
all these actions and this can be
represented visually with this figure
and I find it very very striking when
you link this with actual um
descriptions of what it's like to be in
a severely depressed state so for
instance law describes his own
experience in depression as follows in
depression every tasks take on an as on
an aspect of impossibility I see a task
as far more difficult than it actually
is or I see myself as not being up to
the task so again it's an aspect of
impossibility whereas in quote unquote
normal uh perception there's this of
this kind of tacid or PR effective and
bodily I can what I can do is always
related to these affordances in
depression it's a complete
impossibilities I cannot and this again
this completely illustrates from
experiential perspective how the field
of relevant importances for the
depressed person is almost patent but is
also links with experience of time in
depression so here I have another quote
this is from lot uh he says that in in
his description of his experience in
depression he says I have absolutely no
faith in fact in anything in a mdy way I
see that depression manifests itself as
a crisis of faith not religious Faith
but the almost born Instinct that things
are fluid that they unfold and change
the new kinds of movement the sorry the
new kinds of moment are eventually
possible that the future will arrive I
am in a Time locked place where the
moment I am in with I am in will stretch
on agonizingly
forever and what what is kind of
fascinating for me about these three
points together is that they very very
clearly show how uh affection so this
solicitation and temporality go hand in
hand on the one hand the world is not
soliciting it's not motivating actions
for the subject for thepress subject and
this is also experienced as a lack of
future future is no longer there it is
as if if they are time locked in place
and this precisely shows what I'm trying
to to show that affection this this uh
affordance this the solicitation go hand
in hand with how we experience time
especially as future oriented and this
also shows another point which I further
develop in my my paper but I'm not going
to dwell too much here that this
relationship between affectivity and
temporality is also expressed as what I
may call General feelings so for
instance here lot talks about a a lack
of faith and that lack of faith is quite
literally I would say a feeling in
relation to the whole world so at a the
operative level of intentionality the
world is opened up as lacking not only
motivation but there's no faith towards
it which is more of a feeling domain but
again we can discuss this later on I
just want to show here how in uh
depression we can see that both uh
affect or affection and temporality are
uh
Disturbed so to finish off how can
affection receive temporality if it is
uh deployed in time well it doesn't if
we if we keep ourselves at the
experiential level I would say that
given this kind of phenomenological
analysis now we can go and try to
understand empirically and
neurobiologically the the neural
underpinings of of Consciousness but we
have to take into account this
correlation this co-emergence between
temporality subjective temporality and
affectivity uh and to answer the
question of the title of the paper
nothing comes before time but it comes
hand in hand with affection and that's
it
thanks thank
you thanks awesome thank you
sharing okay first though I hesitate to
use such a time bound word Dean um what
are your what are your
thoughts well first of all thank you and
I apologize for showing up late ju Diego
the last time I saw you you were working
on some things and they was really
impressive and so I I was really excited
about um hearing what you had to present
today I have a quick question for you um
in the active infant Community right now
we are working on trying to put together
something that addresses the ontology of
being inactive inference what does that
mean what's the definitional piece of
that what is it mean to be an active
infer and the the idea that you raised
which is trying to make sense of that
with temporality front of mind okay so
when you put your slides up for example
you had all the images you had the Duck
Rabbit there's a certain stability even
though the agent can pull interpret
ations from that but there's a there's a
kind of consistency a constant to that
whereas if I'm being an active infer if
I'm con the only constant is that I'm
consistently updating I'm always
changing I'm in that flow I'm in that
condition and it's the back and forth
between the relative stabilities and the
and the degree of change that a person
goes through in order to keep up to keep
up with their Niche and understand
that they're enveloped but as you
pointed out there's also these
isomorphisms and this isovist
perspective and this ability to maybe
break timeout into more than one type so
I was just wondering based on the work
that you've done here if you were to try
to come up with an
ontology how would you be able to bring
together the sense of consistency and
the consist and the consistency of
change that is a fascinating question
and I and I think that active inference
is a good lens through which we can
approach this this question not only in
relation to the modeling perspective but
also the phenomenological perspective
because something that I I didn't
mention at least in the presentation but
that's in the paper is that these
anticipations these tcid anticipations
can be understood at not only an
effective level but also at an epistemic
level so for instance Fel would say that
uh sometimes you're walking down the
street and see what might be the shape
of a human being a person and you have a
set of anticipations related to that you
may I would say you anticipate uh you
know talking to the person or you know
engaging different uh activities that
are related to human beings but as you
come closer there's something odd about
this shape it might be either a human
being or a doll K suggests and the
important thing here is that this this
potential this patients kind of are
modalized they become doubtful whoo
would say and that's very reminiscent to
me to what happens in in active
inference so when you know the agent is
updating its inferences it's all it's a
matter of trying to not only take into
account temporal infolding of the world
but trying to get a hold of it right
it's trying to recognize what is going
on outside so there's the constant of
change because the world is constantly
changing and it's also clear in
phenomenology and not only the world is
constantly changing but the subject
Consciousness is always changing this
constant flow that's what defines
Consciousness from a phological
perspective but what I like here is that
what links these two domains together at
the phenomenological level is affection
very literally this embod Dynamics
related to the the world and active
inference does something very similar
you know this inference related to the
policies are what keep the generative
model and generative process together so
there's this constant kind of
correlation and and and Loops between
the agent and the world or the
environment that are also find found in
phenomenology so I would say that if you
ask me about anology and I think that my
coauthor of the other paper we discussed
here last year Zach he would he would
gladly say that this is a process on
and I I agree with that I agree with
that it's the constant is change so one
last Quick followup question if if it is
about
effect then I I know that I can be
conscious I also know that there are
definitions of Consciousness but I'm not
sure that the definitions of consci
Consciousness carry an effect I think
it's only while we're aware of being
conscious
that that effect condition seems to
apply would you agree what do you mean
by an
effect
and in in the in the classic sense of
it's it's here are my emotions these are
the effects that I'm sensing on a on a
moment by moment basis so this is again
goes back to this so we seem to have
this really interesting capacity to be
able to externalize things and strip out
effect because I know poetry can make me
have all of these great
Sensations but once I put the the poem
down and go away they don't follow me
right they stay within the the symbols
on the page I I carry I carry the sense
of Consciousness around with me that's
the being part and so this is again I
don't have an explanation for this but I
just have a lot of Wonders around it
yeah okay so that kind of comes together
with the other thing I didn't mention
too much in the presentation which was
the whole thing about General feelings
so affectivity as I understand that
through the the work of javanna Coletti
is this kind of General uh it's this
lack of indifference towards the world
and this can be understood in very very
different levels it's it's a hierarchy
if you want to put it like that so
emotions I would say are quite complex
you know you have to have an intentional
object most of the time you have to have
certain bodily Dynamics going on there's
an apprisal there's a lot of stuff going
on it's it's this fascinating
combination between cognitive and bodily
components right moods are also super
super complex but I would say even at
the most basic level this this interplay
between affection in the ceran sense and
temporality what you get is not only you
know because you're always anticipating
Bly anticipating the world sometimes
your anticipations might be completely
doubtful right maybe something happened
and this kind of change the whole
anticipatory Dynamics and it's not only
an epistemic thing it's not only like
maybe I should doubt about everything
there's also a lack of trust and again
like Psychopathology shows this quite
clearly I mentioned depression but
there's also a phenomenological research
on trauma and what happens in trauma
people who suffer U uh severe severe
trauma is that they cannot they can no
longer trust other people and the world
and it's not that they explicitly think
about that fact it's simply that the
world appears to be dangerous or you
know as something that might attack me
and this is an effective domain that
it's always kind of I wouldn't say
coloring but it's always kind of
constituting or it's always uh defining
or shaping how we experience the world
so this kind of very general basic basic
domain might change in relation to
emotions which are higher and moods but
it's always that we're always
effectively coupl to the world and this
if if you buy into my whole picture this
effective domain is also active in a
very literal
sense okay I have a slightly different
question how do we go into that micr
temporal
experience like how do we gird or
prepare ourselves or do we go in holding
our hand or are we holding a
wall or how do we enter
into perhaps the the direct
investigation of some of these claims
that are made about in in a way how our
experience arises from our
bodies I think that the best way to do
that is trying
to keep a very tight relationship
between lived experience with
phenomenological analysis and n only the
classical ones we can also think about
qualitative phenomenological uh research
on lived experience made by people like
um andan loots and and others and we can
but we can also have to we also have to
hold together the empirical domain and
that's the whole point of neurop
phenomenology which I truly buy into
so on the one hand a phenomenological
analysis like the one I just proposed
may actually guide how we understand
neurodynamics because you know if you
look at say an fmri you see all these
neural Dynamics going on but by
themselves they don't tell you anything
at all right there're just caal
processes you need to correlate this to
something going on at the at the at the
experiential level it's not only the
fact that we have data but we have a
very very rigorous very strict uh
description of what's going on here and
this may tell us something about how to
interpret and how we understand
neurodynamics but these neur Dynamics
will also probably give us some light on
the experiential
Dynamics uh because maybe there's
something that doesn't fit to well with
phenomenological distinctions and then
we probably have to come back and
reanalyze experience and that's I think
it's more of a kind of social process
right it's we're talking about a social
communities not there's this constant
idea that well not constant but a lot of
people reject these phenomenological
approaches because they think it's just
introspect ction as in you know early
20th century psychology and it's not
really that we have a very strict
methodology and not only that we have
like quote unquote peer review there's a
lot of discussions and I'm entering in a
specific discussion here saying you know
you talk about temporality and
effectivity as distinct no no no they
come together but this is ongoing and I
think I truly believe that there's no
end to this which is kind of a beautiful
thing as well but it's it's trying to
maintain this circulation between
empirical and phenomen phenomenal iCal
levels if we don't keep them together
we're missing part of the
point
another very interesting thing in the
hoero on time Consciousness slide you
had the kind of trace of the past
sedimentation and then the cone of of
protention and then beneath that it said
direction of the flow and the flow was
going to the left pointing
back whereas a common time visualization
would be like well time is going
forward so what is pointing
backwards and why don't you need a
forwards pointing Arrow I wonder whether
I should have just do like a two-way
Arrow because a friend of mine read a
draft of this paper before I published
and and she asked me is it the other way
around and I understand you all mean
because that's true that's kind and and
I'm very like forward looking that's
part of the point what we talking about
you know intentionality future oriented
but I think that when you analyze it in
the way us does it what you not notice
is that the stream of Consciousness is
sinking into the past is like a spear
that is directed towards the future and
that's intentionality but it's always
like a river that is sinking into the
past and that's the reason why uh the
arrow go goes to the left but you might
as well put it in to the right and you
have you know it's just Speer heading to
towards the
future Daniel's not pointing out that he
knows that wayfinders have to get back
before they can go out he's he's he's
conveniently leaving that off he he
recognizes why the arrows going the
direction it
is it just in that
representation reminded me of just like
putting down the
track as we head forward like building a
cliff that's always
being peaked at
over but as we proceed it's like the
ledge just keeps on
extending as we move forward and that
creates the solidity of our
retention um I think so there's also
this metaphor of sedimentation right
that some phenomenologists use quite a
lot they talk about how the what we
experience it's of course retained but
time is sedimented it kind of
metaphorically uh builds the foundations
the soil of what we experience and this
changes our whole experience so we may
understand habits in that way we
experience some some events over and
over and this set it sedimented onto our
Consciousness that's a metaphor of
course and that kind of generates
habitual ways of engaging with the world
and I think that there's something
valuable about emphasizing of this this
sinking into the bit without downplaying
the fact that intentionality is directed
towards the
future sorry I I'm gonna I I really
apologize I really wanted to participate
in this one one Diego because I I think
your work is is fabulous but I now have
to run and go and deal with some
politics in the wilderness so I'm going
to check out right now but thank you
thank you again for uh your fantastic
work thank you as well thank you for
being here at least for a
bit bye-bye okay another kind of
question so you distinguished the active
object
intentionality from the operative passit
or implicit
intentionality so how do we make sense
of a passive
intentionality is it like a desire that
we don't have a control over whereas an
active desire was one that we kind of
selected Upstream to want to
want or or what is the difference
between the active and the passive
intentionality so that's the husan
terminology I don't think it's very
popular nowadays so phenomenologies
often talk about the reflective and
pre-reflective levels so the reflective
is like thematizing explicitly something
whereas pre-reflective is not like in a
temporal way it's more like a condition
for reflection but what I like about the
distinction between Pacific activity is
that it also shows that act like act
intentionality or object intentionality
requires uh degree of activity from the
subject or from the
agent and you know for you to attempt
something you are moving your head
you're moving your eyes you're you know
moving your body even if you do that
somewhat uh by m reflex still a form of
activity right there's some something
that you as an agent as an embodied
agent are doing but regardless of that
there's always this openness to the
world we cannot stop that unless we die
and we don't want you do die to die most
of the time right it's passive in that
sense it's it's kind of almost
instinctual and I wonder whether we may
talk about instincts at that level and
actually there's this very talking about
uh habits again there at some point H
talks about two levels of passivity and
I don't know whether he kind of goes on
with this but I like that because he
says that you know there's like the
primary passivity which is this very
basic effective Dynamics but there's
like a secondary passivity which is pris
the habits it's like a second nature to
us and it becomes passive because you
know when you're very habituated to
something you don't think about it you
don't have to do any kind of reflective
process it just kind of happens and that
tells a lot about how we engage with the
world at a phenomenological level for
sure h and it kind of suggests like the
sedimentation of what is potentially an
a an
active intention in a
moment like if we were practicing
archery what might be active in a moment
or what somebody might cue us to think
about can become sedimented and that's
kind of the process
of our actions becoming habitual or
our our our behavior in the moment over
time it's like you're flowing this color
of sand over the river eventually it
sediments that color without needing
further flow of that color exactly
exactly and that's a
very instinctual perhaps and very
implicit way of understanding learning
right because that's what happens when
we're learning about something at the
beginning especially skills think about
bodily skills if you want to learn to
play the piano the is very difficult you
have to very explicitly move your
fingers and it's awkward and it sounds
horrible but over time this these
movements become habituated and we may
talk about bodily memory or something
like that but it's the same idea you
know it becomes second nature to you
it's it becomes almost
passive H yeah and and thinking about
learning a language
or math or something it's almost like an
applied area of This research agenda
would be to discover potentially to
validate some differences in
learning exercises and then maybe to
suggest new kinds of learning
exercises based upon what could be
attended to in a moment that if it were
sedimented could then be later used as
an implicit
jumping off point like an example coming
to mind is let's just say like an
integral let's just say that the rule
for the integral is like there's always
a number above and below but before even
going into what those are you just
sediment the understanding that there's
always a number above and below it and
kind of swallow that and and sediment it
and accept it and
then
show what those numbers mean
having accepted that they must be
there rather than try to show a new type
of symbol and suggest that the symbol is
a certain way because the math has to be
a certain way and try to
co-sediment um a visual understanding
with a sort of analytical understanding
but maybe some parts could be
sedimented in a different
order yeah I I wonder about that last
bit I mean I don't know nearly enough
about learning more gener but I think it
sounds very roughly correct to me
because if if you think about maths for
instance you know when you have to solve
an equation and you already are skillful
at maths you still have to think about
you know arithmetical calculus processes
right there's an active explicit level
but this is always grounded in a uh and
understanding with which is already kind
of second nature to you you already know
as you said in an integral there's the
number up top the one at the bottom is a
given and you kind of already know
what's the function of it all it doesn't
give you immediately the solution to the
equation necessarily there's an active
process but it's always built on top of
a background of Habitual uh processes
which is prec precisely what a per of
intentionality is trying to capture and
and I mean I I I haven't thought too
much about the relation between maths
and this but what I like about as as an
embodied person as a person who likes
embodied Cog cognitive science uh what I
like about operative interality is that
it's clearly deeply embodied and there
might be a way of connecting you know
these very abstract theoretical
processes like doing math to bily
processes and in active inference that
would be literally the active fit of
active influence isn't
it
yeah potentially there's a that makes me
think of a Memory Palace and leveraging
spatial analogies and protentions I
could walk out of this room into another
room and I'm going to put a fact there
or put a memory there um or associating
a smell or a
sentiment
with another area of information and
then sedimenting that
not so that it is directly
recallable but I guess just when I when
I again to the the trace and the
protention funnel I think about Mike
Levan and the time cone or the time
diamond and we kind of in that
visualization it's almost like the cone
goes off in both directions so we have
the perimeter in the moment which is
like the extent in the now and then the
past is seen as
um I I think one way is probably like
uncertainties over the past whereas in
the uh who Roll On Time Consciousness
slide it was like there's just a single
trace so we could think of it though as
uncertainties or more and more scope of
causal precedence leading in like you
know our grandparents and our great
great grandparents and all this coming
in through the um needle of the
moments um and then like decision making
is jumping off into the protention only
to be answered in the sensory
consequences at the
next
update exactly I that's what I think
that it's a very nice connection between
the active inference conception of of
you know cognition and decision making
and these more phenomenological uh
description because what you get is
precisely this kind of
isomorphic uh mirroring almost between
the structure of the updating of a
generative model in active inference and
the kind of Dynamics the temporal
Dynamics you have in phenomenology and
and what is kind of nice that as you
make more and more complex your your
gentic models you can introduce things
like you know uh effective inference
like Casper's work and I think that
would be an interesting way of trying to
capture some of the effective
domain the effective dynamics that occur
at the Phenom phenomenological level and
that's precisely what I mean that you
have to kind of make this constant
circulation between different domains
like on the one hand the
phenomenology might be able to inform us
how to um kind of organize and kind of
uh think about our generative models and
these generative models may actually
help us understand neural Dynamics and
that's kind of the whole point of what
now we call computational
neurophenomenology but as as a
philosopher and a self-described
phenomenologist I would say you know we
have to start by the phenomenology it
doesn't necessarily mean that
phenomenology trumps everything it
simply means that it's our starting
point because that's literally what we
have that's all we have as as
experiential beings lived experience but
we have to be very careful with how we
analyze it and again it's kind of
fascinating for me this these
similarities between the mathematical
structure of active inference and these
more formal Dynamics in
phology hm it also makes me think about
first learning about xenobiology and
theoretical biology thought well biology
is living real things so if we open the
door to life forms that we haven't
observed or hypothetical life forms what
isn't on the table that's going to be
too
broad because we have enough to
investigate with the forms that are here
so then we have
the starting with what we have and
building out
approach whereas some of this kind of
like I don't know if it would be like
Xeno
phenomenology like thinking about
radically different minds and
systems which in some ways is an
unconstrained Quest because it's going
to be hard to get unique explanations
and predictions about like the
experience of an extraterrestrial that
we haven't seen yet in that social
Quest there are useful factors
identified and in some ways it ends up
being the people's different views on
the plausibility or the
relevance of a given speculation that
reground even what initially could seem
to be like a totally ungrounded question
like what is it like to be a bat or what
is it like to be a cloud or
something you know I I I find that kind
of interesting because that's part of
what I've been what I did during my PhD
it's precisely thinking how these
phenomenological approaches and in
active approaches plus the F might
actually let uh allow us to understand
better biological cognition broadly
understood so I'm not I don't know much
about kind of life as it could be but
Life as We Know it it's clearly you know
bacteria or plants or animals moving
around and trying to survive right
that's the basis of it all but what we
what I what I would say is that for us
to understand that we have to kind of
assume that there's a degree of I mean
very very broadly understood
subjectivity in there I don't want to
say that the bacterium is conscious or
aware or something like that I don't
think so but there is a sensitivity to
the environment you know when the
bacterium is swimming
you know in chemot taxis swimming
towards the glucose there is a sense in
which the bacterian is sensitive to the
environment is affected by it that's a
very natural way of of putting it and
what is fascinating again is this kind
of similarity between these very complex
phenomenological analysis of human
experiences and when we find when we can
see kind of from a third or second
person perspective on other living
beings there's very close similarities
and if we take very very seriously
theeran claimed that the whole point of
phenomenology is to disclose this
invariant structures of Consciousness or
subjectivity or whatever you want to
call it then there there's a case to be
made that uh these invariant structures
may actually speak of the at least the
conceptual basis of what we may call
biological
cognition and I mean that's a massive
project but I think there's something
about that and I think again that active
inference is it's an interesting kind of
bridge between all these different
perspectives because if you say that
active inference is is capable of say
modeling you know biological Dynamics on
the one hand and also uh experiential
Dynamics as you know computational
phenomenology claims then it's it's this
kind of interesting formal bridge
between say biology phenomenology and
neurobiology Etc it's of uh it's it's a
bridge it's a very helpful bridge I
would
say yeah the second
person perspective it makes me think
about the um biography of Barbara mclin
talk who's a biologist studied
transposons and mobile genetic elements
and the biography written by Evelyn Fox
Keller is called a feeling for the
organism kind of alluding to the
career-long quest to have a feeling for
corn genetics in this case and other
genetic systems and so whereas the what
is it like to be a bat is kind of like a
third person firsters
dialectic I'm over here third party to
the bat and I want to get into that
driver's seat and be first person in the
bat and then what would it be like and
so that's kind of like the first third
first third I'm my first and I want to
be its first so I'm its third but then
the second
person which I see in the second person
Neuroscience area is like what is the
feeling
for and the relational component that is
actually a kind of
alternative to swapping first person
perspectives because if it was just
swapping first person
perspectives you don't and you just go
from I
am person I am a bat yep versus you are
a bat is engaging in the second person
and that brings in the social component
of the phenomenological project and
distinguishes it in a way from a kind of
solipsistic firsters eye
agenda yes yes for sure sure for sure
and I think that kind of project is
quite radical in the sense that it it
has very interesting consequences uh in
relation to how we think about science
right because in a very kind of
traditional I would say even dogmatic
way we think about science as this
strive for objectivity like the third
person perspective as such and maybe
that makes sense in in certain Natural
Sciences maybe physics perhaps I I don't
know but in something like biology
you're dealing with another living being
right and it's not in certain cases
might be a third person perspective if
you put it but you know when the
biologist is looking at the bat or the
bacterian or the amoeba or whatever
there's there's a quote unquote social
process going on you know I I the
scientist I'm recognizing you the the
biological system as a biological system
I'm actually noticing something in there
I may not know what it's like to be B
but I know what it's like to be a living
being we have a common ground and that's
that at least from the human perspective
is an experiential common ground and
that's what phenomenology breaks into
the table a way of trying to analyze
this but again it's a very radical
change I would say because at least
biology becomes kind of this quote
unquote social science not in the sense
of Sociology or anthropology but it's a
matter of I'm actually engaging with
this this biological
system and if we build from there
at least at the level of analysis for
organisms maybe not genetics and you
know or population but at least at the
level of organismic
existence I think there might be some
ways of reconceptualizing our
understanding of
life Wow like on the
overemphasizing first person we have the
cartisian thought experiment
hyperbolically overemphasizing the third
person denying interiority we have
behaviorism
only standing outside of the room and
never asking internally
and there's another bridging path that
is very provocative that biology would
be a social science is because yeah that
will be interpreted in a disciplinary
setting but social being like composite
or
Collective yeah and co-active which is
exactly where it feels like biology
should be
yeah exactly yeah I say social science
in the broadest of Senses not I wouldn't
say that again there's a very strong
connection in sociology or anthropology
and biology but social in the sense that
again there is a social connection
between the the the scientist and its
object we're talking about two quote
unquote subjects relating to one another
they're Co co- enacting a world in a
sense and that's that's a very inactive
conception like if you you look at the
works of Francisco or Evan Thompson EO
their ideas that are very consistent
with this approach and I think that
phenomenology may also bring interesting
uh tools to understand this because you
know there's a whole literature and
phenomenology about sociality inter
subjectivity and it's usually
emphasizing how we understand one
another as human beings it's not Sol
systm but the question is what happens
if we try to apply this analysis to our
understanding of other living beings not
only human beings and that opens up a
whole new you know domain for research I
think yeah and perhaps even speaks to
the unhealed Gap with like ecology is
everything that happens on earth except
for human activities that's why it's
human ecology or biology is all living
systems except for the social because
those are the human and so there's kind
of this tension with kind of like are
humans natural and are we part
of the fields and methods that should be
approaching any other kind of
mammal Andor do we rely on more
transcendental methods that wouldn't be
empirically useful in studying like an
insect at first
pass sure I I guess the question would
be if we take this kind of
transcendental path if you want to call
it that way how can
we let's say operationalize this into a
more empirical project because as a
philosopher I'm happy to say we should
do transcendental phenomenology and make
S about transcendental biology but I'm
also quite aware because I work in
interdisciplinary context that that's
not enough that gives you a very
interesting and I would say very strong
theoretical basis but that's not
empirical science right how can you step
from these theoretical claims to making
you know testable predictions and
hypothesis that's the question and
that's a fascinating question I think
yeah and that well maybe you've outlined
an alternative meeting point which is
rather than finding a common molecular
basis between humans and fruit flies I
mean we know that we have proteins
carbohydrates we know what reductionism
is going to find when we're turned into
dust but you're in a way outlining a
path of saying well certainly something
affects a fruit fly and it doeses have a
protention might be a shorter or
different shaped protention but by
rather than trying to
materialize The Human Experience
only and find a common grounding on the
materialized by having a common
grounding in the time
Consciousness then even the
bacterium can be jux opposed with the
human and not on a
material comparation not just because we
have shared material or DNA but because
we have a shared living autopoetic
embedding yeah exactly there's there's
this continuity between what it's like
Quon to be a bacterian and what it's
like to be a human it's certainly not
identical we cannot reduce our kind of
experience to whatever kind of
interiority uh it's there in the in in a
bacterian
we cannot do the other way around either
we can we we recognize experientially
these Dynamics right and I think there's
actually empirical evidence for this
kind of processes we I've read about you
know quote unquote cellular memory how
bacterian when they're swimming in you
know a a milu environment there seems to
be a very very minimal uh degree of
memory or historicity and that explains
a lot of behavior we may have even um
mechanistic approach to this we can
explain this quote unquote minimal
memory from mechanistic perspective and
I'm happy to do that because that's
empir bit but what is interesting that
we recognize that because we experience
that in a perhaps more complex way but
it's the roots of what we call
temporality and affection affectivity
it's at the roots of life and again
that's that's out is that's Matana and I
truly believe that if you buy into the
phenomenological conception you will
naturally tend to this more inactive
conception
all awesome well do you have any last
kind of comments or
thoughts uh no no no not really this
this was been a very good uh discussion
I like this thank you yes well we also
um learned a lot from your work in our
recent shared
protentions paper and it's just exciting
to see all these threads and and
complimenting pieces the puzzle yeah
there's there's an ongoing kind of new
research field that is trying to link
all the different concepts and I think
that's very important because I'm kind
of amazed at the fact that it might I
think it has the power to change some of
our ways in which we understand and do
science uh hopefully we'll
see to find out we'll find out I mean
that's what else can we do wouldn't
expect any other answer wouldn't prefer
any other answer um thank you very much
so good luck with your research and see
you next time thank you thank you Dan
bye bye
bye